<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Ivan Odbratt</title>
    <description>Maybe later</description>
    <link>http://www.ivanodbratt.com</link>
    
      <item>
        <title>Minimum income?</title>
        <description>Should developed nations like the US replace all poverty abatement programs with the guaranteed minimum income?

Yes. By replacing government transfer payments with a minimum income, you could eliminate the welfare trap, reduce overhead costs (less bureaucracy), eliminate poverty, and free people to live their lives as they see fit.

As things stand now, it seems like people in developed nations have converged to the opinion that no one should starve in the streets and kids should have at least some basic level of opportunity. The much more interesting question is what we should do about it.

In the United States at the Federal level we have converged to providing *in kind* benefits through various bureaucracies--think housing assistance, medical benefits, and food stamps. These programs have certain means tested requirements so that only people in need end up using these programs. The problem is not that these bureaucracies end up being inefficient and bloated. Rather, the bigger problem is that various overlapping federal programs all have different thresholds for help. In one program you might lose 50 cents of benefits for each additional dollar you make. Multiplied across four programs, and each additional dollar of income would make you *worse off*. Even worse, some programs might have big drop offs so that after a certain income threshold, you go from receiving a decent amount of assistance to none at all. These effects lead to incentive structures such that people are *afraid to earn more money--afraid to work more*. 

Furthermore, establishing a minimum income would free people to live how they want to. By providing unconditional assistance and letting people choose how they want to allocate their spending, people can choose to go back to school, take time off work to learn a new skill, or even start a new business. I don't know how many Einsteins or Larry Pages are out there waiting tables just trying to keep their heads above water, but I'd be willing to bet that there are a lot. Once you create a minimum income, you create an environment that rewards risk taking. **For the first time in human history the worst case scenario when starting a new business or going back to school is not starvation.**

There will be people that choose to waste their lives away by living off that income. But there are already lots of people wasting their lives away living off of welfare right now. And even worse, **there are already people who are wasting their lives living off of welfare or waiting tables that are too scared to take a risk and make a better future for themselves, their families, and the world.** I don't care who you are. When faced with the choice of the welfare trap where your family will be worse off if you earn more income, you will choose to earn less income, reducing your long-term chances at success in life and depriving the world of your full potential. **When it's a choice between your dignity and food in your kids' mouths, you will choose the food.** 

We have an incredible opportunity in modern society to facilitate the full blossoming of human potential. For the first time in history, we have the opportunity to ensure that everyone gets a chance in life. With the incredible abundance that we have, we can promise that each person will be able to live in dignity. Maybe not in comfort, but at least in dignity. In my opinion, it is the antidote to inequality in capitalist society and the answer to the question to Rawls' question of how we should ensure that everyone benefits from economic growth and technological progress. In an era of increasingly fast change, we need a minimum income now more than ever. It just so happens that we now have the tools to make it a reality.</description>
        <published>2013-12-04 17:58:30 +0100</published>
        <link>http://www.ivanodbratt.com/minimum-income</link>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Advertising</title>
        <description>A great source here is Naomi Klein's *No Logo.*

Her point, which was one of those things that's obvious once it's pointed out, is that we buy images as much as products. 

Look at it this way:

It's been shown that if you add a picture of a sprig of parsley to a can of meat, [people report that the meat tastes better.](http://books.google.com/books?id=VKGbb1hg8JAC&amp;pg=PT96&amp;lpg=PT96&amp;dq=%22that+little+bit+of+parsley+helps%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=XrWj520m0V&amp;sig=wFhN-gAddlk8NS3ljnJeg8jb3EY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=rnqTUtL5HdSwsASPioGAAw&amp;ved=0CCkQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22that%20little%20bit%20of%20parsley%20helps%22&amp;f=false)

Similarly, put a high price tag on a bottle of wine, and [people will prefer that wine](http://www.wine-searcher.com/m/2012/10/expensive-wines-taste-better-study) to the same wine in a generic bottle.

And if people report that it tastes better, we can't really argue with that. They're not deluded--if they say it tastes better, it tastes better.

So, part of the value of the can of meat comes from the meat itself, and part comes from the picture of parsley.

Part of the value of the wine comes from the wine itself--you can't just sell vinegar for $200 and expect people to not notice--and some comes from the price tag.

In other words, the *image* is part of what we're buying. 

Klein's point is that image is often a *large* part of what we're buying. So it actually makes perfect sense that, back in the 1990s, Michael Jordan was paid more to lend his image to Air Jordans than the entire Vietnamese workforce was paid to make them--buyers were getting value from the image as well as the shoe.

And again, people aren't deluded--if owning Air Jordans gets you respect on the playground, then you're *right* to buy them for the image.

So advertising (unlike what many econ texts will still tell you) doesn't remind you that you can get a Coke if you're thirsty. At least, it doesn't only do that. It also conveys and reinforces an image, and to some degree the image is what you're buying.

And keeping an image in people's mind takes a lot more work than just reminding us that a product exists. After all, what does [a bunch of people singing with candles](http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ib-Qiyklq-Q) actually have to do with the experience of drinking caffeinated sugar water? 

If you *don't* keep the image in people's mind, bad things happen to your brand. We can see this with the new Australian law that cigarettes have to be sold in plain packaging (i.e., no branding). Sales have dropped, even though anyone who could buy a cig before the law can still do so. &quot;Most of this industry is about image. It's not about tobacco,&quot; [in the words of a law professor.](http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/australias-plain-packaging-stubs-out-cigarette-branding-prompting-backlash/2013/10/29/317e58cc-3ccd-11e3-a94f-b58017bfee6c_story.html)

That sounds weird, and the Coca-cola company itself blundered badly in the 1980s by not realizing it. They knew that people preferred Pepsi in blind taste tests, and they [changed the formula](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Coke). But people didn't just buy the taste, they bought the image--the familiar old can with the awesome lettering, the sense of tradition, the people singing with candles. There was a big outcry--far louder and more outraged than when, say, politicians take our votes away--and Coke changed the formula back. More important, they changed the *can* back (more or less). In my opinion, if they'd simply gradually changed the formula and not told anyone, nobody would have noticed (the American beer companies turned their beer to dishwater in the 1950s and 1960s and nobody said boo).</description>
        <published>2013-12-04 17:42:13 +0100</published>
        <link>http://www.ivanodbratt.com/advertising</link>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Job-hunting</title>
        <description>Hi there! I'm new to Reddit and new to posting, but I loved this sub-reddit so much I had to make an account. Anyway, on to your question! 

I'm currently also applying for a new job as well. When I first started applying, I felt really good about it and I was super efficient. &quot;Oh shit! That McKinsey guy I met agreed to forward my application to the right people! Wait, what? Google is in the middle of a hiring expansion? Yes!&quot; 

The problem? Simple, you're not going to get all of these jobs. You're just not. And here's the deal, it's tough. You have zero reward coming your way for doing a lot of work, or at the least, zero reward coming in immediately. You say that you are a reasonably disciplined person, and I believe you. Think about all those things you are disciplined about, whether it is getting your work done, getting that crucial workout in or making sure you sleep on time. It all has a reward that's fairly immediate.

The trick, for me, to applying to jobs is to create that carrot on a stick for yourself. Here's what I do and, while this may not work for you, I'm hoping that it will inspire you to find your own &quot;rewards.&quot;

First, I write out all the things I don't like **ON PAPER WITH BIG LETTERS** about my current job. For example, my list consists of something like this:

* No room for growth. I'm stuck in a position where I'm very good at what I do, but I'm constantly bored because I'm not excited about my job anymore.
* My boss now takes me for granted and expects that I'll work much harder and much later than anyone else in the office. I don't mind working harder or longer, but it's now getting to the point where it interferes with the rest of my priorities and talking to him about it did not help.
* I enjoy where I am (marketing/consulting) but I want to move to a field that I think I would enjoy more (strategy/management consulting).

Sweet, I have that list now, right? What do I do with it? Well, this list is all negatives. Now you need positives. Make a list of all the things you want your new job to have. Here's mine:

* Culture. Culture, culture, culture. I want to be friends with the people I work with. I want a company/job that has a great culture and recruits awesome people (not workers, there's a difference).
*  I want to have an impact. I want to feel happy about the work that I do, and not the paycheck that I get because I made someone a lot of money.
* I want my job to be a part of who I am, not something that defines me. In other words, when someone says &quot;what do you do,&quot; a common opener in DC, I want to answer with enthusiasm because I *want* to tell you what I do and not &quot;I'm a PM at so and so firm.&quot;
* My dream job would _________________

Sweet. Got that. Now, when you're applying to jobs, here's what you do. Read the negatives. Take a few sips of water. Stand up. Read the positives. Shout &quot;Woo!&quot; or whatever you want. Sit down, get started. Every time you feel your brain give up, repeat the process. You want to tell your brain that this is important and that there is a reward for this. 

*I know the above paragraph sounds a little trite but let me explain why I do this exactly the way I do. First, I read the negatives. That gets me pumped up. I think, &quot;yeah, I'm tired of being used&quot; or &quot;yeah, I love my boss as a friend but he's just not a good boss&quot; or whatever it is that you dislike about your present situation.&quot; I then take a drink of water. Taking a drink of water, for me, serves as an intermediary to the positives. I'm metaphorically washing away the negative thoughts so I don't dwell on them (this will hurt your ability to apply to jobs). Now that I'm pumped up, but not focused on what I don't like, I move to the positives. Now I'm really getting myself going - &quot;Hell yeah, there are a lot of cool things out there and I'm going to find one I want to do!&quot; Now I stand up, this gets my blood flowing a bit and continues to build that excitement for what's about to come. I shout something to pump myself up (Let's GO!!!) and then I get to it.*

Finally, any and I mean **ANY** time you finish a job application, stop. Take a break. You did it. Feel good about yourself. Smile. I don't care if you don't feel like smiling. Smile anyway. Go look in a mirror. Tell yourself **ALOUD** that you did it. If you have a roommate, tell them. Call your Mom, your girlfriend, your sibling, your best friend, whoever you can call and tell who won't think you're weird for doing so.

It's all about positive reinforcement and remember you can do it. Good luck with your applications and a new job!

As a side note: You will have to do this at least once an hour or two from my experience. That makes sense because taking a 3-5 minute break every hour when you're working breaks up the monotony and makes you work better. This sort of does the same thing with an added emphasis on the motivation factor.</description>
        <published>2013-12-04 17:42:04 +0100</published>
        <link>http://www.ivanodbratt.com/job-hunting</link>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Alone</title>
        <description>There will always be a constant.

I can't even remember when it all began. I don't remember when I was born and I don't recall if I had a name. Sometimes I make up a name for myself but I always forget it again. Of course, a name isn't needed when there is no one else in the universe, but it's nice to have something to call myself. A designation for the collection of atoms that is me. I've decided to call myself &quot;John&quot; today.

Hello. I know you can't really hear me, I know that you're just a figment of my imagination but it's nice to pretend to talk to someone. I've decided that your name is Barbara. I don't know if my words even make sense. Chances are that I've forgotten language too but that hardly matters. I can't talk in space anyway so I'm just thinking really hard and pretending that you're here to listen.

Hello, Barbara. My name is John. It's nice to meet you.

The universe is dark now. Matter spread out over time. Planets slowly dissolved into nothing, the stars went supernova and exploded in a fury of heat and colors. The universe is still here, I suppose, but it's not really much use in this state. There are no suns, no planets or asteroids hurtling through it, none of what made it so glorious before.

You should have seen it, Barbara. It was amazing. Each planet had its own, glorious scenery. Some were colored in ice that perfectly reflected the starlight and some had weather patterns so insane that each day was a glorious, thunderous lightshow. And life! Life was my favorite thing of all. Self-contained replicating systems that interacted and communicated much like we are now. They were perfect. I loved life, I really did. Of course, it had its ups and downs but of all the things the universe had, life was by far my favorite.

Say, Barbara, do you want to hear a secret? I can die. I'm immortal now but if I ever made the conscious decision to die then I would and my particles would dissolve just like the rest of the universe. However, I can't allow myself to do so. I'm not even tempted any longer because I know that I have the most important role of all: There will always be a constant and I'm it.

I have mass. Not a lot, but I have some. Right now, entropy has spread particles perfectly over the universe but I have mass and with it just a tiny bit of gravitational pull. Over the next trillions of years, the particles will slowly move towards me. A small layer of dust at first then slowly more and more until every bit of matter in the whole universe is here at this very spot in a singularity more powerful than anything else the world has ever seen.

It'll hurt, of course. It always hurts. The vacuum of space, the fiery core of the singularity, every part of it makes my body convulse with intense pain, but it's worth it. The singularity won't be stable. It'll eventually collapse on itself and the particles will once again be unleashed into the dawn of a glorious new universe.

It has happened so many times. So very, very many times, Barbara. There must always be a constant because the constant ensures that the new universe will be born. There will be life again someday. Oh, there'll be so much life; whole planets will be covered by it. We may never meet for real, Barbara, but I feel happy knowing that you might one day exist outside of my mind. Sure, your universe will die one day just like all the previous ones but you know what? While it remains, it'll be a glorious splendor of life and it'll make all these dark days worth it. 

Thank you, Barbara. Really. Thank you.</description>
        <published>2013-12-04 17:41:37 +0100</published>
        <link>http://www.ivanodbratt.com/alone</link>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>